Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. So today's דף daf is ל"ו. lamed-vav.
We pick up in the middle of ל"ה עמוד ב'. lamed-hey amud-bet.
We had some very nice and important, rich דפים dappim yesterday, in
particular the whole issue again of מעילה me'ila by קונמות, konamot,
whether it's, and particularly קונם konam because it's borrowing from the word
of קרבן korban
and when it's אסור assur to everybody it's even more like a
קרבן korban and there's a מעילה me'ila concept according to at least
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, maybe even when it's forbidden only on particular
people.
So that was like one particular area that was of course very
significant. And the other thing that I was mentioning beforehand also that
I think is worth sort of just appreciating for a moment, is
that it's one thing to say there's a concept in מעילה. me'ila.
In general, there are two ways that somebody does מעילה: me'ila: one
is by getting הנאה, hana'ah, pleasure, from, you know, benefit from something
that is sanctified, and the other is by appropriating it, taking it
for oneself, giving it to another person and so on. And whenever
one learns מעילה, me'ila, the question is like are those two separate
paths or are they all very, are they all fundamentally one path?
So you could say it's two paths, there's an איסור הנאה issur
hana'ah and there's an איסור גזילה issur gezeilah because הקדש hekdesh owns
the object as well, and you could say it's fundamentally one path.
רב חיים Reb Chaim says it's all a form of גזילה. gezeilah.
So if I take something, get benefit from something that isn't mine,
I'm stealing it essentially, I'm stealing its use from someone, that everything
is an expression of גזילה. gezeilah. You could say the opposite, that
everything is an expression of הנאה. hana'ah. I'm deriving benefit and I
derive benefit either by appropriating or by getting physical benefit. Anyway, what's
particularly interesting is it's one thing when we say there's an idea
of מעילה me'ila by נדרים, nedarim, when I say this thing is
like a קרבן korban that it borrows from the world of קרבנות
korbanot and it changes its status and it makes it forbidden. We
already know that a נדר neder makes something forbidden, so to say
that when I actually get that benefit, that pleasure, that that's also
a concept not just of violating my vow, but my vow created
a certain reality and there's a concept of מעילה me'ila and trespass
and so on, that I mean to me is not so, you
know, is not so far-fetched. But what we had yesterday, it's worth
noting, is a concept of מעילה me'ila even in the sense of
appropriating. So if I say this כיכר kikar is קונם, konam, is
forbidden to me by a נדר, neder, and then I go ahead
and I don't know, give it to a poor person or something,
then I'm עובר over on מעילה. me'ila. Like what benefit did I
get out of that act? I didn't get any benefit. It sounds
like there's an idea of appropriating and how the word of concept
of a נדר neder and a vow that changes the status makes
it like it's owned by some entity that there's a problem of
taking possession and stealing and owning. It's my loaf of bread for
God's sake, like that is definitely an important חידוש, chiddush, going even
one step further in this world of מעילה. me'ila. So that's just
a comment on what was done yesterday. Now we turn to our
משנה, mishna, which continues in this idea of narrowly defining what is
considered to be benefit. If I say I can't get benefit from
a person, not that the person's objects are forbidden to me, but
I can't get benefit from that person, what types of things are
considered to be benefit and direct benefit as opposed to indirect benefit?
So for example, we had already taught that that person can pay
off my creditors, right, it's an amazing idea, saves me millions of
dollars, thousands of dollars, but I didn't get anything directly from that
person. Okay, the person can also return my lost object because that's
my object and even though somehow they're doing a service, they're doing
a מצוה mitzvah act and the object is mine anyway, so that's,
so that's also not a problem. So our משנה mishna similarly, and
maybe because we stopped, we started, let's just read quickly again from
the top of the page of ל"ה עמוד ב'. lamed-hey amud-bet. התורם
תרומתו ומעשרותיו לדעתו. Hatoreim trumato umasrotov leda'ato. He can take my תרומה
trumah and מעשר ma'aser for me with his knowledge. Who the he
is will be discussed in the גמרא, gemara, but that's I mean
an important question. Is it using his grain or my grain? If
it's using his grain, then he benefited me, saving me from giving
that grain. If it did my grain, it was more of just
like some type of a service and it's less clear what exactly,
I mean it'll, well let me put it this way, it's more
clear why that would be allowed.
ומקריב עליו קיני זבים וזבות קיני יולדות וחטאות ואשמות. Umakriv alav kinei
zavim vezavot kinei yoldot vechatatot va'ashamot. He can bring for me, if
he's a כהן, kohen,
offering in the בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, various bird sacrifices that are
brought for somebody who's a זב zav and a זבה zavah ending
their period of טומאה, tumah, or a woman who has just given
childbirth and the various animal offerings that also are presumably, we'll discuss
this in a minute, part of the termination of that process of
טומאה. tumah. ומלמדו, Umelamdo, let's get caught up. ומלמדו מדרש הלכות ואגדות
Umelamdo midrash halachot ve'agadot and he can also be a תורה Torah
teacher for me even if I can't get הנאה hana'ah from him,
אבל לא ילמדנו מקרא, Aval lo yelamdenu mikra, but not פסוקים, psukim,
אבל מלמד הוא את בניו ואת בנותיו מקרא, Aval melamed hu es
banov ve'es bnotov mikra, but he can teach my kids. So again,
what exactly the difference of all that is is interesting. But again,
what we see is a principle that when he is doing something
that is a תורה Torah benefit that I am getting, meaning a
מצוה mitzvah benefit, returning my lost object, that was a service he
did for me, bringing a קרבן, korban, that was a service, taking
תרומות, trumos, that was a service. So as long as I did
not get any additional benefit other than that service, right, that is
considered to be not a הנאה. hana'ah.
And, presumably and to teach me תורה. Torah. Now תורה Torah you
could say wasn't just like a service, he actually gave me something,
if you would, he gave me his knowledge, right? He imparted knowledge
to me. I actually gained from that, it wasn't just some type
of a service. There's actually something that I end up with right
now, which is more תורה Torah knowledge than I had before, very
different than some of those other things where it was just some
service that somebody else could have performed. Here I actually got something,
as it were, not physical, but got something from him. So all
of this is part of this category of מצות לאו להנות ניתנו.
mitzvos lav l'henos nitnu. מצות mitzvos are not considered to be a
form of הנאה, hana'ah, which is a point that I've made before,
which is not—I mean although רש"י Rashi in a number of places
in the גמרא Gemara says, well because they're supposed to be a
burden and a responsibility and not a benefit, which is turning it
into a theological discussion, you know,
and you could say sort of that thing that people say often
right before קדיש Kaddish is the exact opposite of that message of
רש"י, Rashi, right? What does it—what is it? אמר רבי, Amar Rabi,
who is it? No, no, לא נתנו מצות אלא כדי לזכות את
ישראל. lo nitnu mitzvos ela kedei l'zakos es Yisrael.
What is it? רבי חנניה בן עקשיא. Rabi Chananya ben Akashya.
No, it's not רבי חנניה בן עקשיא, Rabi Chananya ben Akashya, who
is it? I think you know who says it...
Oh, yeah, that's it! רצה הקדוש ברוך הוא לזכות את ישראל.
retza Hakadosh
Baruch Hu l'zakos es Yisrael.
רבי חנניה בן עקשיא. Rabi Chananya ben Akashya. רצה הקדוש ברוך הוא
לזכות את ישראל לפיכך הרבה להם תורה ומצות. Retza Hakadosh Baruch Hu
l'zakos es Yisrael lifikach hirba lahem Torah u'mitzvos. Anyway, every time you
say אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו, asher kideshanu b'mitzvosav v'tzivanu, presumably you're saying
that it's an opportunity and a wonderful thing, not just a burden.
But anyway, bracketing the theological point, the real point is that הלכתית,
halachically, benefit is only measured in physical real world terms. So some
type of financial benefit or some type of physical benefit that I
got, bodily pleasure and benefit that I got, but things that are
even some of the most important things for us in the world
are not included—are not, you know, are not הלכתית halachically considered to
be הנאה hana'ah because הלכה halacha is very this-worldly. So for example,
just as though this applies not related to מצות, mitzvos, you're not
allowed to get הנאה hana'ah from a dead body, from a corpse,
but you can use a corpse for anatomical dissection and to learn
the medicine. Now why is that? I mean that's a tremendous benefit.
You're learning the skill of medicine, you're gaining the knowledge through anatomical
dissection, you're getting that benefit from the corpse
because that is not considered to be הלכתית halachically benefit. It is
not physical pleasure, it is not monetary benefit and so on. And
the same if somebody gives me תורה, Torah, I mean what can
be better in the world right than תלמוד תורה כנגד כולם Talmud
Torah k'neged kulam and the becoming—the wisdom and the knowledge and the,
you know, and the religious sort of benefit of תורה, Torah, nevertheless
that's not considered to be הנאה. hana'ah. So therefore the person can
now—then the only remaining question is, right, so we'll have to deal
with the מקווה mikvah aspect, right? So that certainly in terms of
when the sort of physical thing I got from that person is
a—not physical, the thing I got is a is the fulfillment of
a מצוה, mitzvah, the learning of תורה, Torah, that's not a physical
benefit. And that presumably informs these other parts as well, doing things
like returning a lost object and taking תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros and
bringing קרבנות korbanos to the degree that those are also מצות, mitzvos,
we don't say, oh, he did a service for you and therefore
you got some benefit because he didn't—no, he was doing a מצוה
mitzvah and therefore a מצוה mitzvah service is not, you know, is
not considered the same. Now although again that's, you know, you could
argue that that's a little different. I needed somebody to take my
תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros and this person did it. Nevertheless, since it
was the performance of a מצוה, mitzvah, it's not considered to be
benefit. Yes?
Does that mean it technically should be אסור assur to profit from
the sale of an organ that you harvested and
then—yes, that is true, I mean that—but yes, but that's a different
conversation.
Yes, assuming standard like we said about מקרבן mi'korban that would mean
it's like a כהן, Kohen, so can it mean that like let's
say I just said, oh, you know, I know you have this
קרבן korban hanging out there and you need it to be brought
and I
can't—it could be, but that's not how the גמרא Gemara understands it
and that would raise more serious questions because then there is like
actually the whole aspect about like benefiting me from the saving of
the money in terms of that thing. And that does remain is
an interesting question in מצות לאו להנות ניתנו, mitzvos lav l'henos nitnu,
which is let's
say—let's say the fact
that—let's say I actually saved money as a result of it. So
if I—if I say, I don't know,
you know, let's say I have, I don't know, candles made out
of חלב, cheilev, forbidden fat, well actually I'm allowed to get הנאה
hana'ah from חלב. cheilev. But anyway,
let's—you know, let's say I don't know, I said these candles are
אסור עלי בהנאה, assur alai b'hana'ah, right, and it was חנוכה Chanukah
and I needed to use the—and there was and I didn't have
any other candles and if I couldn't use those candles I'd have
to go ahead and buy candles at the store. So there's a
benefit I'm getting is not only the מצוה mitzvah benefit, it's—it's because
I'm able to use them it's saving me money, right? However the
money I would have spent is only to get the benefit of
the מצוה, mitzvah, so is that considered I am getting הנאה hana'ah
from them or not getting הנאה hana'ah from them? So that's an
interesting question. All right, so let's take a look now at the
גמרא. Gemara. So that's the basic principle here of the משנה. Mishna.
That's like a פלודא דרבי יוסי pluda d'Rabi Yosei in a way,
yeah.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu,
they raised the question: הני כהני שלוחי דידן הוו או שלוחי דרחמנא
הוו? Hani kohanei shluchei didan havu o shluchei d'Rachmana havu? או שלוחי
דשמיא? o shluchei deShmaya? So Kohanim כהנים, Kohanim, are they in the
Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, are they considered to be doing
our service? Or do they represent Klal Yisrael כלל ישראל? Klal Yisrael?
Or are they serving God? It's interesting to look at the various
pesukim פסוקים pesukim about this, about how the Kohanim כהנים Kohanim are
identified and how the Levi'im לוים Levi'im are identified, and whether they're
considered who they're considered to be representing, right? But it's basically like
I go ahead and I bring my—if you want to think about
it, like where's the threshold when I bring my korban קרבן? korban?
Do I go ahead and I bring my korban קרבן korban and
I give it to the Kohen כהן Kohen and now essentially I've
given my korban קרבן korban to God and then I like walk
away, right? Or no, I give it to the Kohen כהן Kohen
and then the Kohen כהן Kohen is sort of representing me and
it's being given to God when it's being like offered on the
Mizbe'ach מזבח. Mizbe'ach. Okay, so obviously halachically it's only considered a good
korban קרבן korban when it's being put on the Mizbe'ach מזבח, Mizbe'ach,
but at what point has I—you know, have I now put it
into God's domain? Or and that's if the Kohanim כהנים Kohanim are
sort of seen as sort of part of the Beit HaMikdash בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash and representing God and God's domain, to what degree
are they just representing me and bringing my korbanot קרבנות? korbanot? So
this is a question that the Gemara גמרא Gemara asks in a
number of places. Elsewhere the Gemara גמרא Gemara concludes that the Kohanim
כהנים Kohanim are considered to be God's emissaries because they couldn't be
my emissaries. If they were my emissaries, it would mean that I
would be—you can't make somebody your emissary and your agent for something
you can't do yourself. So since I'm not myself allowed to bring
the korban קרבן, korban, they can't be seen as my agent—unless I'm
a Kohen כהן—they Kohen can't be seen as my agent, so they
must sort of be seen as God's representatives, which is quite fascinating
because anybody who remembers learning Zevachim זבחים Zevachim and all those discussions
about pigul פיגול pigul and so on, in terms of like whose
intent is it that can disqualify the korban קרבן, korban, right? It
really focuses on the intent of the Kohanim כהנים, Kohanim, of the
people that are doing the act, right? But if they are like
my representative—if they—so if they're my representatives, you would see—you would think
that my intent would also be highly relevant, right? And if they're
God's representatives, right, then it makes a little bit more like more
sense that as soon as I give it to them, I'm sort
of done with my role. But anyway, we'll take a look at
that. So that's the question: are they considered to be, you know,
our representatives or God's representatives? L'mai nafka mina למאי נפקא מינה? L'mai
nafka mina? What would be a consequence of this of this way
of phrasing it? So l'mudar hana'ah למודר הנאה l'mudar hana'ah to somebody
who is forbidden to get benefit. Im amarta deshluchei didan havu אי
אמרת דשלוחי דידן הוו, Im amarta deshluchei didan havu, if they are
our representatives, mehani leh מהני ליה, mehani leh, he's giving me benefit,
v'assur ואסור v'assur and it's forbidden.
Meaning if I can't get benefit from this Kohen כהן Kohen and
he's offering up a korban קרבן korban for me, I'm getting benefit
from him if he's my representative. V'im amarta shluchei deShmaya ואי אמרת
שלוחי דשמיא, V'im amarta shluchei deShmaya, shari שרי. shari. But if it's
God's representative, it's permissible. Why? What's—now the logic being that there are
things which the actual act itself is not considered to be a
benefit, but nevertheless for somebody to be seen of as my direct
agent and representative, then that person is doing something for me. So
for example, right, if—I don't know, we said the other day—if you
paid off my creditor, okay, because it was like indirect or whatever,
you know, that's not—ironically, that's not considered a hana'ah הנאה. hana'ah. But
if I make you an agent and say, "Go pay off my
creditor," then in that act of doing something, you are doing something
on my behalf and that is—the very fact that you are—have been
appointed by me and are doing something on my behalf, whatever that
activity is that you are doing is considered to be a hana'ah
הנאה. hana'ah. So even if very—the bringing of a korban קרבן korban
for you is a mitzvah מצוה mitzvah act and not considered in
itself a hana'ah הנאה hana'ah because it's just a mitzvah מצוה mitzvah
activity and so on—maybe just is the wrong word—but anyway, because it's
a mitzvah מצוה mitzvah activity, but to be my agent and representative
in the performance of something, right, that is a hana'ah הנאה. hana'ah.
Let's say—let's take something that's totally silly. Let's say I would like
this rock thrown into the river, okay? No clear reason why that's
a benefit. And I say, "Be my—be my shaliach שליח shaliach to
go—go throw this—you know, be my representative to go do this." So
in that role, in that capacity of being my—you know, the person
that I have appointed and doing something on my behalf, that the
Gemara גמרא Gemara says would make it constitute hana'ah הנאה. hana'ah. So
therefore, if—therefore, if they're our shluchim שלוחים, shluchim, how can the Kohen
כהן Kohen be makriv מקריב makriv korbanot קרבנות korbanot for me? That's
the Gemara's גמרא Gemara's question. So let's see what the answer says.
Tashma detnan תא שמע דתנן, Tashma detnan,
makriv alav kinei zavim מקריב עליו קיני זבים. makriv alav kinei zavim.
Im amarta shluchei didan אי אמרת שלוחי דידן, Im amarta shluchei didan,
if they're our representatives, kamahani leh כמהני ליה, kamahani leh, he's doing
a—benefiting me, he's serving as my representative, so that should be forbidden.
Why does the Mishna משנה Mishna say it's permissible? So the Gemara
גמרא Gemara says no. Im amarta—so the Gemara גמרא Gemara says: v'ta'ameich
וטעמיך, v'ta'ameich, liktani makriv alav korbanot ליתני מקריב עליו קרבנות. liktani makriv
alav korbanot. If that's true, that he can do all korbanot קרבנות
korbanot for me, why didn't it just generically say he can bring
korbanot קרבנות? korbanot? Ela mechussar kapara sha'ani אלא מחוסר כפרה שאני. Ela
mechussar kapara sha'ani. It's different when it comes to mechussar kapara מחוסר
כפרה. mechussar kapara. Mechussar kapara מחוסר כפרה Mechussar kapara are people for
whom a korban קרבן korban is not brought to atone for any
sin—although they do some bring a chatat חטאת—it's chatat done to change
a state from being tamei טמא tamei to tahor טהור, tahor, something
that often very much has to do with a personal status, not
just tum'ah טומאה tum'ah acquired from the outside. If I touch a
corpse, it's a very heavy tum'ah טומאה, tum'ah, we just read that
in the Torah תורה, Torah, but that's only—but—but
there's
no korban קרבן korban that's associated because it's... from the outside. If
I have a certain type of an of a bodily emission and
a flow or something of that nature or מצורע, metzora, something that
very much is about my person and my body, then to change
that status from טומאה tumah to טהרה taharah we need a bring
of a קרבן Korban and sometimes it includes, and not sometimes, it
includes a חטאת Chatas because one of the mistakes is to think
that חטאת Chatas is all about a sin whereas חטאת Chatas is
really about cleansing. Okay and that's called מחוסרי כפרה, mechusrei kaparah, people
who lack atonement, but really it's a phrase that specifically means that
need a קרבן Korban to be brought to change their status from
טומאה tumah to טהרה. taharah. Okay and the גמרא Gemara points out
that the משנה Mishnah specifically emphasizes those. Why does it specifically emphasize
those? Why doesn't it just say they can bring a קרבן Korban
for me? So אימא דליסי מכל קורבנות אלא מחוסרי כפרה שאני. Ima
dilma mikol korbanos ela mechusrei kaparah shani. People that are מחוסרי כפרה
mechusrei kaparah bringing a קרבן Korban for them is a different
category. דאמר רבי יוחנן D'amar Rabbi Yochanan because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says הכל צריכין דעת חוץ ממחוסרי כפרה. Hakol tzrichin daas chutz mi-mechusrei
kaparah.
Everybody needs to have their you need their knowledge that a קרבן
Korban is being brought for their behalf except for somebody who is
a מחוסרי כפרה mechusrei kaparah and the קרבן Korban is brought to
change their status.
How do you know? שהרי אדם מביא קרבן על בניו ובנותיו הקטנים
Sheharei adam meivi korban al banav u-benosav ha-ketanim because for people that
are מחוסרי כפרה mechusrei kaparah a father can bring for his children
his
his sons and daughters.
שנאמר Shene'emar as the פסוק pasuk says זאת תורת הזב, Zos toras
ha-zav, בין גדול בין קטן, bein gadol bein katan,
whether the זב zav is
an adult or a minor a קרבן Korban can be brought for
them. So you can so we learn from the פסוק pasuk that
a קרבן Korban can be brought for a minor when it is
coming to change their status when they're מחוסרי כפרה mechusrei kaparah the
קרבן Korban is coming to make them from טומאה tumah to טהרה.
taharah. Now this is a very important conceptual point about the difference
of קרבנות. Korbanos. Normally a קרבן, Korban, right whenever you get to
the beginning of ויקרא Vayikra some rabbi's going to say in a
sermon that the word קרבן, Korban, you know the word sacrifice is
not the real translation of the word קרבן, Korban, the word קרבן
Korban comes from the word קרב karev to get close to God
and it's about right drawing close through the bringing of something which
is all very true right? But is that what a קרבן Korban
of a מחוסרי כפרה mechusrei kaparah is about? Is it about drawing
close or is it about to be you know it is somehow
the instrument that is done to effect this what's considered this metaphysical
cleansing and purification and transfer of status? So that's what it's saying
is the difference. If I bring an עולה olah or שלמים shelamim
let's say a נדר neder I'm trying to get close to God
bring this you know somehow this act in a very physical way
allows me to to connect to God in some religious way metaphysical
way and so on. Or if I did a sin right although
there's obviously the element of cleansing but a normal sin as well
חז"ל Chazal also understand that a חטאת Chatas like we understand the
normal process of תשובה teshuva comes with וידוי viduy comes with you
know comes with remorse comes with a a confession
and the bringing of a חטאת Chatas or an אשם asham when
it's not in a normal case is also about me making a
statement and you know connecting to God. But what it's saying is
that's not true about מחוסרי כפרה. mechusrei kaparah. מחוסרי כפרה mechusrei kaparah
is it's just serving as an instrument to cleanse you. So the
same way if you touch a corpse we're going to sprinkle ashes
of a פרה אדומה parah adumah on you if you were a
woman who gave childbirth or a man who had a certain bodily
emission or whatever we are going to bring this קרבן Korban for
you and that will somehow be the ritual that will cleanse you.
If that's what's happening you don't even have to be aware of
it because it's not about you in person connecting to God in
some way and this קרבן Korban is an expression of that connection
or of that atonement process or whatever. It's just a ritual that's
being done to cleanse you so it does not require your knowledge.
Okay so that's a very important and radical distinction about the thing
that these are very different type of a קרבן. Korban. Now how
is that relevant for us? It's relevant for us because remember we
said the bringing of a קרבן Korban for somebody is not in
itself הנאה. hana'ah. The reason the גמרא Gemara thought it would be
הנאה hana'ah is that if you're doing it it's if I basically
have to appoint you as my representative and you're doing it as
my representative then you are directly doing you're not just doing something
that I benefit from you're actually acting on my behalf and if
you're acting on my behalf then that's considered an הנאה. hana'ah. So
what the גמרא Gemara says is the משנה Mishnah says the כהן
Kohen can bring קרבנות Korbanos for מחוסרי כפרה. mechusrei kaparah. For those
he won't act on the person's behalf I meaning he'll do the
act for the person but it won't be as if the person
is appointing him and making him his representative. And because that is
not necessary in this case. In this case he can be oblivious
to what's being done. This is a case where the כהנים Kohanim
do not have to be שלוחי דידן. shluchei didan. So even if
normally we're the ones that should be bringing the קרבן Korban and
the כהן Kohen serves as instead of me to be bringing the
קרבן Korban and my representative and therefore that would be an הנאה
hana'ah problem, by מחוסרי כפרה mechusrei kaparah I don't have to be
the one bringing it somebody else could bring it and it could
be work for me. Like somebody could sprinkle the ashes of the
פרה אדומה parah adumah on me. Somebody else could do it and
therefore there’s
no and therefore
there’s no need for it’s not a problem of even if generally
כהנים kohanim are representatives, here they would not be, they would not
have to be and therefore it would not be a problem of
איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. David, you had a question.
I think you said as far as becoming closer to השם Hashem
also because they're now allowed to...
Well,
it enables them to do that, but it's saying that, right, sure,
that's what now they're enabled to do, but it's not seen as
though that act is... the same way when you sprinkle the ashes
of the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, that's not seen as an act
of bringing the person closer to God in that act, right? That's
just something that removes the טומאה tumah that now allows that to
happen, right? Yes. Did we
say דעת... da'at...
Yeah.
Did we say דעת da'at very generally though, like I'm doing it
for you at some point, right? Like it's not that I'm bringing
it for you today and you know it's going to be me
for all my family, but you just have to know that it's
being taken
care of? I mean eventually the person should find out so that
he knows he can eat קדשים, kodashim, but I'm saying that the
act of הקרבה hakravah does not require his his knowledge.
No no no, right, okay, but דעת da'at is just... but you
mean it can't be like, you know, that I'm... it can be
even post facto, right? It doesn't have to, I don't have to
tell you before
or after or
that I'm doing it?
No, meaning, oh that, you mean in other things that need דעת,
da'at, like I don't have to know which is the כהן kohen
who's bringing it and exactly at what time it's being brought and
so on. Right, a general awareness suffices, that is correct. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, אלא מעתה ela me'atah says the
גמרא Gemara לרבי יוחנן. l'Rabbi Yochanan.
So now we're going to digress a little bit on this question
about which קרבנות korbanos require דעת. da'at. According to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, זאת תורת היולדת, zot torat hayoledet, this is the תורה Torah
for a woman who gives childbirth, so בין קטנה בין
גדולה,
bein k'tanah bein
gedolah, so logically we'd say whether an adult or a minor the
word תורה Torah would be inclusive and again this is a מחוסרי
כפרה mechusrei kaparah so it should work for a minor. So what's
the big deal? Yes, so let it work for a minor. So
that's the גמרא Gemara is going to question. So קטנה בת לידה?
k'tanah bat leidah? How could that include even a minor?
Since when do minor girls give birth? והתניא ve'ha tanya רב ביבי
Rav Bibi קמי דרב נחמן, k'mei de'Rav Nachman, שלש נשים משמשות במוך.
shalosh nashim m'shamshos b'moach.
Three women have to use a מוך moach which is a type
of a of a sponge that would be put in in the
vagina sort of but it close to the sort of entrance of
it. That's relevant because it's not it should not be confused with
a with a diaphragm which is less of a halachic issue than
a מוך. moach. קטנה ומעוברת ומניקה. k'tanah u'me'uberet u'meneket.
So who are the three women? A young girl, a pregnant woman,
and a nursing woman. They we they have to make sure they
don't get pregnant. קטנה שמא תתעבר ותמות. k'tanah shema tit'aber v'tamut. A
קטנה k'tanah because we're afraid that she'll get pregnant and that she'll
die as a result of the pregnancy and childbirth. So therefore she
uses this form of birth control. And then it goes on for
the reason the other women also because it will be dangerous to
their fetus and or the child that they are nursing you know
if you're in these circumstances so if they were to if they
were to conceive. Now the גמרא Gemara assuming that well depending on
how you read the גמרא Gemara it might be it might be
assuming that a pregnant woman could also could conceive and then it
would endanger her fetus but that's a debate of רש״י Rashi תוספות.
Tosafot. Anyway the גמרא Gemara says you see from this issue what?
Under twelve and a half, under twelve. Now by the way you
should... so a yes, so for a based off partly what you're
asking is it's assuming that a girl under twelve is having sex
then yes that gets to the whole underage marriage discussion although we
have discussed before that although קידושין kiddushin was underage the גמרא Gemara
does indicate that at least in most circumstances the נישואין nisuin and
when they started their their married life together and were actually having
sex waited a few years but anyway the other thing worth pointing
out is that this גמרא Gemara is very central for contemporary discussions
of birth control whether it's about the issue of diaphragm or a
condom and the key question just to say very parenthetically about this
is how to interpret the word משמשות. m'shamshos. Is it these three
women must use a מוך moach and other women are allowed to
or right so therefore actually there's no halachically would not be a
problem using this as a form of birth control it's just these
three are obligated to use a מוך moach or is it these
three women may use a מוך moach and other women are not
allowed to? Right big difference right of whether you read the word
משמשות m'shamshos as must or may because in what does it imply
in terms of other women. Anyway the relevance for us is that
you see it assumes that a minor girl will not survive childbirth
and therefore how could the תורה Torah be coming along to be
including in the word זאת תורת zot torat by the case of
the יולדת yoledet even somebody who is underaged. Now of course the
funny question is is that the is that maybe it just means
it most it will often happen doesn't mean it will always happen
that she won't survive but that's the גמרא's Gemara question. So the
גמרא Gemara says what do you do with זאת תורת zot torat
since it cannot be including a minor girl so the גמרא Gemara
says ההיא זאת תורת היולדת בין פקחת בין שוטה. hahi zot torat
hayoledet bein pikchat bein shotah. No that's that is coming to include
a similar case that the person does not have to be aware.
aware that a קרבן korban is being brought for them and they
don't need the person to represent them in the bringing of a
קרבן, korban, but it doesn't include a minor, it includes a woman
who is a שוטה, shota, is somebody that is
not in charge of her mental capacities and therefore that person cannot
bring her own קרבן korban or certainly cannot provide
ודעת veda'at because they're not aware they don't have sufficient halakhic understanding
and awareness and nevertheless a קרבן korban can be brought for them.
שכן אדם מביא קרבן על אשתו שוטה, Sheken adam mevi korban al
ishto shota, a man can bring a קרבן korban for his wife
even if she is a שוטה, shota, even if she does not
have her mental faculties. כדברי רבי יהודה, Kedivrei Rabbi Yehuda, like the
words of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דתניא Detanya which taught a ברייתא,
braisa, רבי יהודה אומר אדם מביא קרבן עשיר על אשתו. Rabbi Yehuda
omer adam mevi korban ashir al ishto. So the first point it's
making here is not that the wife is really, it's quoting רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, not so much to include the case of a
wife who is a שוטה, shota, but to say that the husband
is obligated financially to bring the קרבנות korbanot for his wife and
the one interesting relevant aspect about this is, let's say the wife
does a particular sin or whatever that obligates a קרבן עולה ויורד.
korban oleh veyored. Now קרבן עולה ויורד korban oleh veyored is a
sliding scale קרבן korban based on a person's finances, they either can
bring as a little as birds or a מנחה mincha or as
much as a major animal there, so like a sheep or whatever
depending on the case. Now, my wife goes ahead and we're living
two thousand years ago and of course she doesn't have any work
outside of the home and she doesn't have any money of her
own and even if she earned some money every now and then,
the הלכות halakhot of the כתובה kesuva say that I get to
put it in my bank account because I agree to provide for
her. She has obligated in a קרבן עולה ויורד. korban oleh veyored.
So where does she go on the sliding scale? She technically is
a pauper, she doesn't have a penny to her name, therefore she
should be allowed for her to bring the lowest end of the
scale and the ברייתא braisa actually tells us משנה, mishna, she says
no, it goes by my financial ability because basically I am responsible
for her financially to provide קרבנות korbanot if she needs a קרבן
korban and therefore it goes by my financial ability and that's the
key חידוש chidush of this משנה mishna אדם מביא קרבן עשיר על
אשתו, adam mevi korban ashir al ishto,
that you bring a קרבן korban of a rich person, meaning based
on the husband's finances for his wife because it's his financial responsibility
to pay for the קרבנות korbanot for his
wife. וכל קרבנות שחייבת, Vechol korbanot shechayevet,
and he's obligated to actually pay for all קרבנות korbanot that she's
obligated in, שכך כותב לה, shekach kotev lah,
because this is what he writes for her, ואחריות דאית לי עלך
מן קדמת דנא, ve'achrayus de'is li alach min kadmas denah, the responsibility
that you have on me from before this. Now, where does he
write this for her and what does it mean? Our גרסא girsa
of the גמרא Gemara sounds like it's written in the כתובה. kesuva.
Of course that leads to a large discussion. What? The husband assumes
financial obligations that the wife has from before the marriage because that's
what it sounds מן אחריות דאית לי עלך, min achrayus de'is li
alach, obligations that you have from before this. So it sounds like
the husband assumes the wife's previous financial obligations. That is not true.
That is not true in terms of כתובה kesuva obligations. So most
people switch the גרסא girsa here or have a different גרסא girsa
that says when he divorces her, he writes in his the receipt
of the כתובה kesuva that you have, I am basically free now
from all prior obligations and all financial obligations are considered to be
have been paid up and I'm free from all prior financial obligations
incurred during the marriage, and somehow that generic thing of all obligations
is understood to include even קרבנות. korbanot. Why we interpret that to
include even קרבנות korbanot I have no idea. To what exact evidence
is being brought from this line of either the כתובה kesuva or
the receipt is not clear. Bottom line what's relevant for us is
that all that's relevant for us is the idea that a husband
pays for his wife's קרבנות. korbanot. Now paying for his wife's קרבנות
korbanot is not the same as saying that he goes ahead and
does it without her awareness of it. He goes ahead and takes
care of it and just you stay at home, I'll take care
of the business. It's very different to say she gives him the
bill and he writes out the check as opposed to saying he's
the one that actually goes ahead and is מקריב makriv it. But
somehow that's what we're saying. Once we establish this idea that it's
his financial responsibility, we're also assuming that he can bring קרבנות korbanot
for her, especially the ones that are מחוסרי כפרה, mechusrei kappara, the
ones that don't require דעת. da'at. And therefore even if she's a
שוטה, shota, even if she doesn't have mental faculties, he can still
bring קרבנות korbanot for her. That's what we see the פסוק pasuk
is including and again reinforcing this approach of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
that מחוסרי כפרה mechusrei kappara do not require their awareness that a
קרבן korban is being brought for them because it really is coming
just to cleanse and change their status. Yes, Rachel? Sorry, when would
a שוטה shota need her husband to bring a קרבן korban for
her? When would a שוטה shota need to have a קרבן korban
brought for her? She wants to go and eat enter into the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. It's פסח. Pesach. Oh no, you were saying
קטנה. ktana. The other case is a שוטה. shota. So my wife
wants... it's a case of חנה, Chana, right? We go up to
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. I got to go bring her some
קרבנות korbanos to eat. In the end, it was a case of
a שוטה. shota. Let's say חנה Chana be... okay. קרבנות, korbanos, yes.
חנה Chana can be technically someone's wife. Yes, that's so, yes. In
which case, the obligation is her husband's, not the father. Correct. And
does the rabbi תנא tanna understand the basic biology that you don't...
you can have a child when you can have a child. Yeah.
What do you mean, that it's possible to have a child even
under twelve? Well, you have a child when you begin to menstruate.
Right. But that often would make a girl not a קטנה. ktana.
I mean, that's a whole discussion in the גמרא. Gemara. I mean,
like twelve, thirteen, something like that. Right. But it's not ideal to
have a child at that time, you would probably die. Okay, so
that's the question whether the גמרא Gemara assumes that... so the גמרא
Gemara here seems to understand that the girl would die, although the
רן Ran says and if the girl wouldn't die, it's following the
opinion that the very act of childbirth defines the girl no longer
as a קטנה. ktana. Because, sort of as you said, if somebody
is
not a קטנה ktana because we're talking about
whether, you know, they
hit puberty. Right. The act of intercourse wouldn't.
Right. All right. So now, picking up at the top, so
now, in all of these cases, all
these cases
is to make exceptions of them so that the כהנים Kohanim are
שלוחי דידן.
shluchei didan. Yes, so the גמרא Gemara
is saying that in principle, you could say the כהנים Kohanim are
שלוחי דידן, shluchei didan, and the reason it's okay in the משנה
Mishnah is the משנה Mishnah is talking about מחוסרי כפרה, mechusrei kapara,
which do not require them to represent us. But now we're not
done. So let's take a look at top of ל"ו עמוד א'.
lamed vav amud aleph.
We're finally officially on today's דף.
daf. מתיב רב שימי בר אבא. Masiv Rav Shimi bar Abba. So
רב שימי בר אבא
Rav Shimi bar Abba asks, we have a ברייתא braisa that says
that sort of
deals with a similar case to the משנה Mishnah and says the
following: אם היה כהן, im haya Kohen, if the person who
I can't get benefit from is a כהן, Kohen, יזרוק עליו דם
חטאתו ודם אשמו, yizrok alav dam chataso vedam ashamo, he can sprinkle
the blood of a חטאת chatas and an אשם. asham. So that
sounds like he can
bring any קרבן korban for me, which would show that he's not
my representative. So the גמרא Gemara says no, maybe it doesn't mean
any קרבן, korban, maybe it means דם חטאתו של מצורע ודם אשמו
של מצורע. dam chataso shel metzora vedam ashamo shel metzora. Maybe it's
talking about a חטאת chatas and an אשם asham that are brought
for מצורע, metzora, which are also the case of מחוסרי כפרה. mechusrei
kapara. So we, again, maybe a כהן Kohen cannot bring any קרבן
korban for me if I can't get
הנאה, hana'ah, maybe he would
be considered my representative and the only cases that we say
it's allowed would be the special exception of מחוסרי כפרה. mechusrei kapara.
Okay, דכתיב, d'ksiv, the verse says זאת תהיה תורת המצורע, Zos tihye
toras hametzora, בין גדול בין קטן, bein gadol bein katan, the same
idea, it
has the word תורת, toras, which means whether for an adult or
a minor, same idea, מחוסרי כפרה mechusrei kapara does not require the
person's דעת da'as and therefore the כהן Kohen is not the person's
representative. Okay, תנן. t'nan. So we're going to keep on trying to
now discuss this about שלוחי דרחמנא shluchei d'rachmana or שלוחי דידן, shluchei
didan, שלוחי דשמיא. shluchei dish'maya.
הכהנים שפיגלו במקדש,
hakohanim shepiglu be-mikdash, when כהנים Kohanim do פיגול, pigul, they have a
thought about eating the קרבן korban at the wrong time, במזידין חייבין,
b'mezidin chayavin, if they do it willfully then they have to pay
me for damages because then they destroyed my sheep here, they did
an act that they knew would make it invalid, they were to
blame. So that's what the משנה Mishnah says. Now, השוגגין, hashogegin, if
they were unintentional, meaning let's say they thought they were שוחטין shachting
a קרבן korban that they thought was a two-day קרבן korban and
it was a one-day קרבן korban and it was an honest mistake,
okay, then they're exempt, even though the קרבן korban is פיגול pigul
because they had the thought to eat it at the wrong time,
they're שוגג shogeg so they're exempt from damages, אלא שפיגולן פיגול, ella
shepigulan pigul, but their פיגול pigul is still effective and the קרבן
korban is still invalid. Now we want to understand why the פיגול
pigul is effective. אי אמרת בשלמא שלוחי דשמיא הוי,
iy amarta bishlama shluchei
dish'maya havei, if they're seen as basically God's representatives, so היינו שפיגולן
פיגול, hainu shepigulan pigul, we understand that even when they're unintentional, their
פיגול pigul is effective, right, they, because they're doing a physical act
to the קרבן korban and slaughtering it or whatever, they can define
its identity even if they're not representing us, right, but if somebody's
actually physically doing something to something then their intent can define its
identity, and we understand that even if it was an honest mistake
they did the wrong thing and they made it פיגול. pigul. אלא
אי אמרת שלוחי דידן, ella iy amarta shluchei didan, but if they're
seen as our representatives, הוו, havu, אמאי פיגולן פיגול, amai pigulan pigul,
why when they make a mistake is it a good פיגול? pigul?
לימא ליה, leima ley, why can't I say to the כהן Kohen
who made this honest mistake: שליח שויתיך, shlicha shavisach, one minute buddy,
I gave you my sheep there to serve as my representative, לתקוני
ולא לעוותי, litkuni velo l'avusi, I did it to make you my
שליח shaliach for my benefit, not to do it in a way
that was going to come to bite me to hurt me? So
therefore in that act of שוחטין shachting it with your... פיגול pigul
thought, you were not my שליח. shaliach. I never wanted to make
you a שליח, shaliach, you know, in that capacity. Now of course
the point is, so to say that even when he's מזיד. meizid.
So the ר"ן Ran says no, no, if you gave me your
or let's say I gave you, if I have because I'm the
I gave you my קרבן, korban, right? And you went ahead and
you said, I don't care, you know, that I know what type
of a קרבן korban this is or whatever, that this is supposed
to be a one-day קרבן, korban, I'm going to have כוונה kavanah
to eat it for two days or whatever. In that moment you
the כהן, Kohen, you're clearly acting you've gone rogue. You are not
acting, right, you're outside your authority as my שליח. shaliach. You are
acting on your own desire, you know, and so on. So fine,
you're just coming along and damaging my object because you're a כהן
Kohen and you're entitled to שחט shecht it or whatever, it's considered
an act of פיגול. pigul. That there's no question when you're willfully
having the wrong intent. But if you made an honest mistake, you're
trying to act in my parameters and based on the agency that
I've given you, you're trying to do it. And when accidentally you
weren't, then neither of us would have wanted in that case for
you to have been doing what you did. And therefore could be
considered that in that case, you're not my representative and it's not
a פיגול. pigul. Okay, so and therefore since it is a פיגול
pigul though, it shows that the כהן Kohen is not acting as
my representative. Because if you were my representative and it was an
honest mistake, then neither of us would have wanted that to have
been seen as, you know, being my agent for that. And therefore
as a מודר, mudar, to bring it all the way back to
that, they could still offer a קרבן korban so to speak on
my behalf because he's really not my שליח. shaliach. Exactly. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, אמר יצחק, amar Yitzchak, you could say שאני
גבי פיגול דאמר קרא לא יחשב לו, shani gabei pigul de'amar kra
lo yeichashev lo, it should not be considered for him, he should
not have that thought, מכל מקום. mikol makom. So maybe somehow those
extra words are coming to say that even though even if it
were to be operating under the constructs of שליחות, shlichus, somehow whenever
you have that thought, it has the effect of invalidating the קרבן
korban even though you could have made an argument that that person
in that case is not my שליח. shaliach. So this גמרא Gemara
does not have a conclusive argument. It says it's possible to say
that כהנים Kohanim are always representing me. And even though they're always
representing me and somehow פיגול pigul still works even בשוגג, beshogeg, but
fundamentally they're representing me. And the time that I can get it's
okay when I get say I can't get הנאה hana'ah
is the limited case of מחוסרי כפרה.
mechusrei kaparah. Because in מחוסרי כפרה mechusrei kaparah there they're not representing
me, they don't have to represent me, and therefore I can get
they can do it for me in that case. However, although this
גמרא Gemara does not conclude whether they're considered שלוחי דידן shluchei didan
or שלוחי דשמיא, shluchei deshmaya, other גמרות Gemaros
conclude that they are considered to be שלוחי דשמיא shluchei deshmaya at
least fundamentally seen as sort of representing God in the temple. כהנים
משולחן גבוה קזכו, Kohanim mishulchan gavo'ah kazchu, is that a separate issue?
That's a slightly separate issue. Okay. All right. So anyway, so that's
point number one. They can be מקריב קרבנות makriv korbanos why? Because
as we said, the fundamental point in this משנה mishnah is they're
not serving as my שליח, shaliach, as my direct representative, whatever they're
doing I didn't get direct benefit from them. And in the act
they were not doing it on my behalf. So the first thing
we have to say by the קרבן korban cases is that they're
not doing it on my behalf. Either because it's specifically מחוסרי כפרה
mechusrei kaparah or in general by קרבנות korbanos they're not seen as
my agent, as my שליח. shaliach. Right. Now we get to we're
going to go and fully expand רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan statement before
we move on in the משנה. mishnah. גופא, Gufa, let's go back
and look at what we said quoted from רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
אמר רבי יוחנן כל צריכין דעת חוץ ממחוסרי כפרה שאדם מביא קרבן
על בניו ועל בנותיו הקטנים. amar Rabbi Yochanan kol tzerichin da'at chutz
mimechusrei kaparah she'adam meivi korban al banav ve'al benotav haketanim. אלא מעתה,
Ela me'ata, because you can bring it for your minor children, therefore
מחוסרי כפרה mechusrei kaparah does not need their awareness. גמרא Gemara says
אלא מעתה יביא אדם חטאת חלב על חבירו, ela me'ata yavi adam
chatat cheilev al chaveiro, make the same argument that I can go
ahead and bring a חטאת חלב. chatat cheilev. A חטאת chatat for
a sin is normally sort of, you know, given the label of
חטאת חלב. chatat cheilev. Because חלב cheilev is like a classic example
of some
type of forbidden food that's טריף treif you
would say בשר בחלב basar bechalav probably or חזיר. chazir. Well guess
what, neither of those do you get כרת karet for, so neither
of those would you bring a חטאת. chatat. The only thing you
would bring a חטאת chatat for would be חמץ בפסח, chametz bePesach,
דם, dam, and חלב. cheilev. Those are things you get כרת, karet,
maybe you could come up with a few others. But so anyway,
so חטאת חלב chatat cheilev since a lot of good examples of
talking about how did somebody do this type of a sin in
this way and that way and so on, are you obligated חטאת
chatat or not? The easy examples to use was that a person
ate something forbidden. So the classic example that we use to describe
a sin offering for a sin is a sin offering of חלב,
cheilev, of forbidden fat, which is a sin that you get כרת
karet for and therefore you would bring a קרבן korban if you
did it בשוגג. beshogeg. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, why not
say that for a sin offering you can also bring a קרבן
korban for me? So I went ahead and I accidentally ate חלב
cheilev and Michael knows I'm a little hard up for money and
Michael is going to just go ahead and take his animal and
sanctify it, and not only that, he's going to go ahead and
bring it to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash for me and all
this without telling me. That should be good. Why should it be
good? יביא אדם חטאת חלב על חבירו שכן yavi adam chatas chelev
al chaveiro sheken אדם מביא על אשתו שוטה adam meivi al ishto
shota כרבי יהודה ke'Rabbi Yehuda because a man can bring for his
wife even if she doesn't have her right faculties because remember the
statement about רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that a husband is financially responsible
for his wife's קרבנות korbanos did not mention specifically יולדת, yoledes, right?
Just generally said a husband is responsible. So the גמרא Gemara says
if a husband is responsible for his wife's קרבנות korbanos maybe it
means all of her קרבנות. korbanos. Maybe it means even if she
even her even a חטאת chatas for a sin. And if that's
true that a man can bring for his wife and we're going
to now assume he can even bring for his wife if she's
a שוטה, shota, let's just use that as an example that you
could therefore we can learn from that that you could always bring
a sin offering for somebody else. But wouldn't his wife be different?
I mean but that's the yes, but let's assume that we're going
to use that as a paradigm. We used it before for one.
So the גמרא Gemara says ואמר רבי אלעזר ve'amar Rabbi Elazar why
does רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar say הפריש חטאת חלב על חבירו לא
עשה כלום hifrish chatas chelev al chaveiro lo asa klum that if
you separated out a חטאת חלב chatas chelev for your friend it
was not meaningful because a person has to bring their own קרבן
חטאת, korban chatas, presumably even sanctify their own קרבן חטאת. korban chatas.
So so why is that? Why now that's consistent with רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said the only exception is
מחוסרי כפרה. mechusrei kapara. Okay, so we get that that's consistent with
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, but we want to know how is it
different than the case of the husband bringing a sacrifice for his
wife? So why is it different? Or maybe it's not different. So
the גמרא Gemara says you know what? It's not different. גמרא Gemara
says the following. It says אשתו שוטה היכי דמי. ishto shota heichi
dami. One minute. You got it wrong. You're never going to have
this case by a wife who is a שוטה, shota, not of
her faculties and the husband would bring a normal sin offering for
her. Why not? Let's take a look. אי דאכלה כשהיא שוטה ei
de'achla kesheihi shota if she ate the forbidden fat when she was
not of her right mind, so לאו בת קרבן היא, lav bas
korban hi, then she's not deserving of a קרבן. korban. Right? Somebody
who is a שוטה shota doesn't have their mental faculties is not
considered to have done a transgression. ואי דאכלה כשהיא פקחת, ve'ei de'achla
kesheihi pikeshas, if she ate it when she was of her right
mind ונשתטית venishtatis and now she is a שוטה shota and now
the husband is going to bring a קרבן, korban, האמר רבי ירמיה
אמר רבי אבהו, ha'amar Rabbi Yirmiya amar Rabbi Abahu, רבי ירמיה Rabbi
Yirmiya said in the name of רבי אבהו, Rabbi Abahu, אמר רבי
יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
אכל חלב והפריש קרבן ונשתטה achal chelev vehifrish korban venishtata if somebody
ate חלב chelev forbidden fat and separated out a קרבן korban and
then they went through some period of where they of not having
their faculties it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara talks about these states
as turning on and off, right? I mean, right? I mean is
the גמרא Gemara talking about somebody that has some type of manic
depressive different episodes or other types of when they can be go
come in and out of maybe people who have alzheimer's or other
types of degenerative diseases. Of state and not a trait. Right exactly.
And that people could have certain types of states where they move
in and out from. So that's not a descriptor of a person
it's a descriptor of a state of being. You're right. I mean
it is interesting that the הלכה halacha very often directly goes to
descriptors personal descriptors like the תורה Torah speaks about we were just
mentioning a זב zav and a זבה zava or whatever the תורה
Torah says if a man has a flow זב zav is a
verb right if if something flows or if a woman has a
flow זוב דמה zov damah but then in the הלכה halacha it
becomes the name of the man. He's a זב, zav, she's a
זבה, zava, right? Is the name of the woman. So here too
like the person is a שוטה shota or שוטה. shota. But in
the end that's just a shorthand it's sometimes not because right because
it's not a permanent state. Right. Unlike an identity issue or something
like that. Exactly. How do you tell in the Hebrew words when
you're describing a state or a trait? You gotta look at the
full context. I mean I'm serious you don't. So that's absolutely true
I mean in terms of the language issue here as well that
it's not just using recognizing this as a state and not a
permanent condition but it's actually the word שוטה shota now we see
by the way does not refer to a full identity issue. So
therefore וחזר ונשתפה vechazar venishtapa so אכל חלב והפריש קרבן ונשתטה achal
chelev vehifrish korban venishtata so somebody did the sin and was deserving
of a קרבן korban and then they separated out a קרבן korban
and then they went into a state where they didn't have where
they were not of right mind וחזר ונשתפה vechazar venishtapa and now
they're better. So פסול pasul the קרבן korban has become invalid in
the interim. How did the קרבן korban become invalid in the interim?
הואיל ונדחה ידחה ho'il venidcha yidcha since while the person was a
שוטה shota the קרבן korban could not be brought
so it was at a state where it was unbringable. That is
seen as something about the identity of the קרבן korban and once
the קרבן korban becomes unbringable for a certain period it becomes considered
פסול pasul and cannot be used again. So now this person would
have to separate out another animal. And now we'll have to praise...
Something like that. Now what's relevant for us is, what's clear is,
that you cannot bring a קרבן korban for somebody who is a
שוטה. shoteh. When somebody is a שוטה, shoteh, it's not just that
it required the, you know, I mean,
you know, whether it's because the bringing of the, of the קרבן
korban requires דעת, da'as, or whether it's because it's a question about
the state of the person—you know, like in order to stand trial
you have to be of right mind, right? In order to have
a קרבן korban brought for you, you have to be of right
mind. One way or the other, it can't be brought for a
person when they're a שוטה. shoteh. So when we say a person
can bring, a man can bring קרבנות korbanos for his wife is
obligated financially, and even if his wife is not of her right
mind, we would be limiting ourselves to the cases of, of a
מחוסרי כפרה, mechusre kapparah, of the specifically the קרבנות korbanos which are
about cleansing and changing the state. Those are the ones that we've
established based on רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan that a per—that that do
not require the דעת da'as of the person for whom they're being
brought. But all other קרבנות korbanos do require the דעת, da'as, and
including a man bringing קרבנות korbanos for his wife, the only קרבן
korban he could bring for his wife without her awareness, and when
she's, or if she's not in her right mind or whatever, would
be the מחוסרי כפרה. mechusre kapparah. The other things require her to
be of right mind and require her awareness like all other קרבנות.
korbanos. Whoa, you just put two things together, that's interesting. If the
woman were a שוטה shoteh and she was also, and she was
also a יולדת, yoledes, right, that would be an effective קרבן korban
that he would bring, so to speak, on her behalf because she's
a שוטה shoteh though at the same time? Doesn't matter, but that
would be okay if, yes, that would be okay for—and we know
it's okay. Why do we know it's okay? Because we have that
statement of אדם מביא על אשתו שוטה adam meivi al ishto shoteh
before, and what we're just doing is we're limiting it to cases
where... But what about the statement נדחה ידחה? nidcha yidacheh? That would
be an—that when it was אחלב achachaleiv the הפריש. hifrish. That's exactly
what we're doing, we're distinguishing between חטאת חלב, chattas chelev, sin offerings
which are about sin, and the specific category which we've identified as
the exception, which is מחוסרי כפרה. mechusre kapparah. So that we're maintaining
as the exception. All right. Let's look for... shh. It's a very,
it's a very interesting thing. From the perspective of sin, the person's
not a human being. From the perspective of a function, the person—I
don't know if I'd say not a human being, but you're not
liable for transgressions and you're not in a state of require—of able
to be atoned, whereas if it's a question of a ritual cleansing,
it's still relevant. I know. All right, we're getting to the—shh, no
more discussions. We're getting to the bottom of the דף. daf. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, והעמוד. v'ha'amad. Okay, אלא מעתה ela
mei'ata says the גמרא, Gemara, יביא אדם פסח על חברו, yavi adam
pesach al chaveiro, שכן אדם מביא על בניו ובנותיו הקטנים. sheken adam
meivi al banav uvnotav haktananim. So a person should be able to
bring a קרבן פסח korban pesach for his friend, if we want
to use as the model what you can do for your children.
And this is basically going back, Michael, to a point you made,
meaning before the whole model that you can, that you don't need
דעת da'as for a מחוסרי כפרה mechusre kapparah is because a father
can bring certain קרבנות korbanos for his children who are a זב
וזבה. zav v'zava. So the גמרא Gemara is saying is, and essentially,
if like, since when can you learn from what a father can
do for his children and a husband for his wife to normal
situations? And if you're going to make that type of a claim
that you can use that as a model for, you know, non-familial
contexts, let's apply it to things beyond מחוסרי כפרה. mechusre kapparah. So
we tried to apply it to normal חטאת chattas and we said
actually it's not true by normal חטאת, chattas, a husband can only
bring for his wife for מחוסרי כפרה. mechusre kapparah. But okay, let's
look in another context. Let's look at a קרבן פסח. korban pesach.
A father can do that for his children, and if you can
use what a father can do for his children as a model
for other people, then I should be able to bring a קרבן
פסח korban pesach for you without you explicitly being part of the
group. And we know the whole process of being part of a
group of קרבן פסח korban pesach is you have to do—right, you
have to be מנויו, minuyav, you have to be part—you know, get
together as a group beforehand. So how do we know a father
can do it for his children? שכן אדם מביא על בניו ובנותיו
הקטנים. sheken adam meivi al banav uvnotav haktananim. אלמה אמר רבי אלעזר—well
alama amar Reb Elazar we know you can bring, like, we take
that for granted. אלמה אמר רבי אלעזר, alama amar Reb Elazar, why
does רבי אלעזר Reb Elazar say, הפריש פסח על חברו לא עשה
כלום, hifrish pesach al chaveiro lo asa klum, that you can't bring
a קרבן פסח korban pesach for your friend? He has to actively
participate. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבי זירא, amar Reb Zeira,
שה לבית אבות לאו דאורייתא. seh l'veis avos lav d'oraisa. When a
father brings for his children, right, minor children, without them actively participating
in the group, that's not a biblical concept. Really biblically, you do
not have to bring for your children, and and therefore, and if
you wanted to bring for them when they were adults, they would
have to actively participate. The idea that שה לבית אבות, seh l'veis
avot, a family and one person brings automatically on behalf of his
whole family, that's not really a biblical concept. Okay, I know, but
what it means is is that the בית אבות beis avot is
understood to be the group that actively joins together, as opposed to
the fact that the—automatically the nuclear family unit that the father automatically
is bringing for his kids, even his minor kids. גמרא Gemara says
that is not, right, so exactly. וממאי, umi'mai, now how do you
know that's not true? ומדתנן, umi detnan, האומר לבניו, ha'omer l'vanav, somebody
says to his sons, הרי אני שוחט את הפסח על מי שיעלה
מכם ראשון לירושלים, harei ani shocheit es hapesach al mi sheya'aleh mikem
rishon l'yerushalayim, I'm going to bring the קרבן פסח korban pesach for
the one who gets first, you all—first you to Jerusalem. I'm going
to bring the קרבן פסח korban pesach for the guy who gets
here first, that's who I'm bringing this קרבן פסח korban Pesach for.
כיון שהכניס ראשון ראשו ורובו, Keivan shehechnis rishon rosho verubbo, once the
first son gets his head and the most of his body into
the environment, crosses the line, gets into ירושלים, Yerushalayim, זכה בחלקו, zacha
bechelko, he gets his portion of the קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, ומזכה
את אחיו עמו, umezakke et achiv immo, and his brothers also now
get a portion together with him. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, how did that work? ואי אמרת שה לבית אבות דאורייתא, ve-im
amarta seh le-veit avot d'Oraita, if you basically have this concept of
שה לבית אבות seh le-veit avot biblically that you needed them to
explicitly, really be included in the father's פסח, Pesach, אבישרא קאי ומזכי
להו? avbisra kai u-mazki lehu? So the thing is already meat, how
can he go ahead and have them get a portion in it?
Meaning the father already שוחט shocheit the קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, and
the son shows up after the father has שחט shachted it, after
it's already meat. How does he retroactively get a portion in the
קרבן פסח? korban Pesach? Now you could say: what do you mean?
He got it because the father said: 'When I'm שוחט shocheit it,
I have in mind the one who's going to get here first.'
It's sort of like יש ברירה. yeish breira. Okay, so fine. So
that works for the guy who got there first. But how does
the guy who got there... the father never said he would do
it for the other brothers? How does he then transfer his rights
and share it with the other brothers? It's already a piece of
meat. He can't do that. So the fact that somehow he's doing
that even though the פסח Pesach wasn't שחט shachted for the other
brothers shows that the other brothers really do not need the קרבן
פסח korban Pesach brought for them. Now we're talking again that they
are minors. Okay, so you've got these kids, they're minors. What's going
to happen is they're going to eat from the קרבן פסח korban
Pesach that night. Okay, but because they're minors, they don't need the
פסח Pesach to have been שחט shachted on their behalf. They're minors.
Now of course you would say, if they're minors, how are they
eating from a קרבן korban that they didn't participate in? Aren't they
doing some sin? You're not supposed to eat from my קרבן פסח
korban Pesach if you didn't participate. How can my younger kids do
that? All right. So somehow we're saying since they're not obligated in
the קרבן, korban, they're also not prohibited against eating from it if
they're not part of the group. If they're גדולים, gedolim, it's a
different story. We're going to assume that they're קטנים. katanim. Okay, so
here's the idea. The idea is, what we're saying is, when I
bring for my minor kids, it's not like they really need it
brought on their behalf and I am bringing on their behalf. If
that were true, then we could use it as a model that
somebody else could bring a קרבן פסח korban Pesach for me even
if I'm not aware of it. What we're saying is, they don't
need it brought on their behalf. They're minors. They don't need it
brought. And they're going to eat with my קרבן פסח korban Pesach
whether or not I שחט shachted it for them because they're minors.
They're not obligated. They're allowed to eat from my קרבן פסח korban
Pesach but it was not brought on their behalf. And the proof
that it doesn't need to be brought on their behalf is this
case where I only שחט shachted it for one kid, for the
kid who came into ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and all the rest of the
kids are eating. Even though it was already meat by the time
we said 'oh let's also make them part of it.' But it
wasn't שחט shachted for them and they're still eating. So you see
when it comes to my minor kids, I don't have to bring
it שחט shachted on their behalf. Okay? ואי אמרת שה לבית אבות
דאורייתא, ve-im amarta seh le-veit avot d'Oraita, if biblically I have to
שחט shacht it on their behalf, אבישרא קאי ומזכי להו? avbisra kai
u-mazki lehu? And how could it be that it's already meat and
now I'm saying 'oh and by the way you kids can also
have a part of it'? Clearly, if I'm only bringing them into
it after I שחט shachted it, it's only because I don't have
to שחט shacht it on their behalf. אלא למה להו דאמר להו
אבון? ella lamma lahu de-amar lehu avuon? So why did I say
to them the first one that gets here I'll make you a
part of it? Not because הלכה halakhically I have to have my
kids in mind, but כדי לזרזם במצוות, kedei le-zarzem be-mitzvot, in order
to get them a little alacrity that they should push themselves to
get to ירושלים Yerushalayim and not שלעפ schlep so much. תניא נמי
הכי, tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly, מעשה היה, ma'aseh hayah, there
was a story, וקדמו בנות לבנים, ve-kidmu banot le-vanim, and actually the
daughters beat the kids' sons in order to get to ירושלים Yerushalayim
first. ונמצאו בנות זריזות, venimtzu banot zerizot, and you see that the
daughters were the ones that had the sort of alacrity, ובנים שפלים,
u-vanim shephelot, and the sons were the ones that were like at
the bottom of the barrel. Now what that exactly proved, number one
it shows that the point is to motivate them, and number two
is that it doesn't say that my sons can't eat from the
קרבן, korban, it just says they showed that they were real losers.
Okay, but it doesn't say that they're not allowed to eat from
the קרבן. korban. So in the end what the גמרא Gemara is
saying is, the reason my minor kids eat from my קרבן פסח
korban Pesach is not because I have to include them in the
שחיטה shechita of the פסח Pesach and I'm allowed to include them
and it has to be brought on their behalf. It wasn't brought
on their behalf. They're minors. They're not obligated for it to be
brought on their behalf. It wasn't brought on their behalf or whatever.
Okay, it wasn't brought on their behalf, but they're allowed to eat
from the meat of the קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. But once it
doesn't have to be brought on their behalf, you can't use this
as a proof that I can bring for somebody else who is
obligated to bring the קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. Okay? So the fact
that my kids eat from my קרבן פסח korban Pesach is not
because I am bringing it on their behalf. שה לבית אבות seh
le-veit avot is not דאורייתא. d'Oraita. I am not. The only thing
I can do for somebody without their awareness, the only thing I
can really do for a קטן Katan or for my wife who's
a שוטה Shoteh or whatever, and something without somebody's awareness is this
case of מחוסרי כפרה Mechusrei Kappara because that's about a cleansing and
that's really not about a person's bringing of the קרבן. Korban. Okay,
now onto today. So we're behind.